<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Science &amp; Programming</title>
<link>https://julia-kaeri.github.io/src/posts/</link>
<atom:link href="https://julia-kaeri.github.io/src/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.43</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 12:31:30 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Report on Plastic Scintillator Radionuclide Identification Technology</title>
  <dc:creator>Julia_KAERI</dc:creator>
  <link>https://julia-kaeri.github.io/src/posts/plastic_scintillator_eng.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
노트
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Google research 에 의해 생성되었음</p>
</div>
</div>
<p><br></p>
<section id="introduction" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Introduction</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Radionuclide identification technology plays a crucial role in various fields such as nuclear safety, nuclear security, environmental monitoring, and medical applications. It is particularly essential for preventing the illicit trafficking of nuclear materials and monitoring radioactive contamination(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>). In the medical field, it is important for accurately identifying and managing radioisotopes used in nuclear medicine diagnostics and treatments.<sup>1</sup> Radionuclide identification technology is also utilized in industrial settings for process control and safety management.</p></li>
<li><p>Plastic scintillator-based radiation detectors are one of the widely used technologies in the field of radiation measurement.</p>
<ul>
<li>Plastic scintillators are composed of a plastic matrix and a fluorescent substance (fluor).<sup>2</sup> When radiation enters a plastic scintillator, it converts the energy of the radiation into light in the visible or near-ultraviolet range through the scintillation phenomenon.<sup>3</sup></li>
<li>Plastic scintillator detectors offer advantages such as cost-effectiveness<sup>4</sup>, fast response speed<sup>5</sup>, ease of fabrication in various forms 4, and robustness suitable for portable devices.<sup>6</sup></li>
<li>Due to these advantages, they are widely used in various applications such as radiation monitoring devices, portable dosimeters, and radiation monitoring systems (Radiation Portal Monitors, RPMs) for preventing the illicit trafficking of radioactive materials.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Problem Statement: Plastic scintillator-based detectors have low gamma-ray energy resolution, making it difficult to accurately and reliably identify radionuclides. This is mainly because Compton scattering is the dominant gamma-ray interaction mechanism, and it is also attributed to the low energy resolution characteristics of the scintillator itself.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</p></li>
<li><p>Scope and Objectives of the Report: This report aims to analyze in detail the principles, limitations, and various technologies and recent advancements in plastic scintillator-based radionuclide identification technology, including energy-weighted algorithms and machine learning approaches. It also aims to highlight innovative solutions to overcome the inherent limitations of plastic scintillators and enhance their radionuclide identification capabilities.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications:</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Insight 1</strong>: The widespread use of plastic scintillators in fields like RPMs, despite their low energy resolution, suggests a trade-off between</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong> : Plastic scintillators are inexpensive and easy to handle, making them ideal for large-scale deployments (e.g., RPMs) where cost is important. Fast response time is critical for quickly inspecting moving objects. However, the inability to accurately identify radionuclides necessitates the development of alternative or complementary technologies.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Insight 2</strong>: The increasing interest in machine learning and advanced algorithms indicates a strong effort to extract more information from the limited spectral data provided by plastic scintillators, thereby overcoming the physical limitations of the detector material itself. This reflects a broader trend of applying advancements in data science to scientific instrumentation.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: Since it is difficult to improve the inherent energy resolution of plastic scintillators, researchers are focusing on enhancing their analysis capabilities through computational methods. This trend shows the growing importance of software-based solutions in the field of radiation detection.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="operating-principles-of-plastic-scintillator-radiation-detectors" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="operating-principles-of-plastic-scintillator-radiation-detectors"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Operating Principles of Plastic Scintillator Radiation Detectors:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Scintillation Mechanism: When radiation (mainly gamma rays for radionuclide identification) interacts with the plastic scintillator material, it excites the molecules.<sup>7</sup>
<ul>
<li>The excited energy is transferred to the fluorescent substance (fluor). Fluors are organic fluorescent compounds (e.g., anthracene or bis-methylstyrene) doped inside the plastic to enhance scintillation properties.<sup>8</sup></li>
<li>The excited fluor molecules return to the ground state, emitting photons in the visible or near-ultraviolet range.<sup>9</sup> This flash of light is the scintillation phenomenon.</li>
<li>The intensity of the emitted light is proportional to the energy of the incident radiation.<sup>10</sup></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Key Features Related to Energy Spectroscopy:
<ul>
<li>Light yield: The number of photons produced per unit energy (generally lower compared to inorganic scintillators like NaI(Tl)).<sup>11</sup></li>
<li>Scintillation efficiency: The efficiency of converting the kinetic energy of incident radiation into detectable light.<sup>12</sup></li>
<li>Decay time: Generally very short (2-4 nanoseconds)<sup>13</sup>, suitable for fast detection and high count rates.<sup>14</sup></li>
<li>Density and Effective atomic number: Low (mainly composed of carbon and hydrogen), so the dominant gamma-ray interaction mechanism is Compton scattering.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Ely2008TheUse">Ely et al. (2008)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Dominant Gamma-Ray Interaction Mechanisms:
<ul>
<li>Compton scattering: An incident gamma ray interacts with an atomic electron, transferring some of its energy to the electron and scattering.<sup>15</sup> This is the dominant process in plastic scintillators, producing a continuous energy spectrum from the incident gamma ray’s energy down to a minimum energy (determined by the Compton edge).(<span class="citation" data-cites="Ely2008TheUse">Ely et al. (2008)</span>)</li>
<li>Photoelectric effect: The gamma ray is completely absorbed by an atom, ejecting an orbital electron (more likely at lower gamma-ray energies and in materials with high atomic numbers; less significant in plastic scintillators).<sup>16</sup></li>
<li>Pair production: The gamma ray is converted into an electron-positron pair near the atomic nucleus (occurs only when the gamma-ray energy exceeds 1.022 MeV; less significant in many common radionuclide detection applications).<sup>17</sup></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Role of Photosensors:
<ul>
<li>Photomultiplier Tubes (PMTs): Vacuum-based devices that detect and amplify the faint light emitted from the scintillator, converting it into an electrical signal. They emit electrons from a photocathode through the photoelectric effect and perform electron amplification at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynode">dynodes</a>.<sup>18</sup> They require a high-voltage power supply for operation.<sup>19</sup></li>
<li>Silicon Photomultipliers (SiPMs): Solid-state photosensors that offer advantages such as small size, low-voltage operation, and insensitivity to magnetic fields, making them increasingly used as an alternative to PMTs in portable applications.3 They can achieve energy resolution similar to PMTs in some scenarios.<sup>20</sup></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-1">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Insight 3</strong>: The low effective atomic number of plastic scintillators causes Compton scattering to be the dominant interaction with gamma rays, which fundamentally limits the ability to obtain the discrete energy information needed for high-resolution energy spectroscopy and direct radionuclide identification.
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: The probability of photoelectric absorption, the process that yields the desired full-energy peak, is highly dependent on the atomic number of the detector material. The low atomic numbers of carbon and hydrogen, which constitute plastic scintillators, mean that Compton scattering is the primary process. This results in a continuous energy spectrum rather than the distinct peaks needed for clear radionuclide identification.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Insight 4</strong>: The choice of photosensor (PMT or SiPM) can affect the overall performance of the detector system, such as sensitivity, power consumption, and suitability for various environments (e.g., the presence of magnetic fields), but it does not change the fundamental limitations of energy resolution imposed by the scintillator material itself. The primary role of the photosensor is to efficiently convert the light generated in the scintillator into an electrical signal. The information content of the light, limited by the physics of the initial gamma-ray interaction, remains the same regardless of the photosensor used.
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: Both PMTs and SiPMs can detect the faint light from plastic scintillators. While SiPMs offer advantages in size and operating characteristics for certain applications, the scintillation light produced in the plastic is a result of Compton scattering events, which inherently broadens the energy spectrum and obscures the unique energy signatures of individual radionuclides.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="challenges-in-radionuclide-identification-using-plastic-scintillators" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="challenges-in-radionuclide-identification-using-plastic-scintillators"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Challenges in Radionuclide Identification Using Plastic Scintillators:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Detailed discussion of inherent limitations hindering accurate radionuclide identification:
<ul>
<li>Low Energy Resolution: Typically in the range of 10-15% at 662 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BkeV%7D"> (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E%7B137%7D">Cs), significantly lower than inorganic scintillators like NaI(Tl) (6-8%) or HPGe detectors (&lt;1%).(<span class="citation" data-cites="Mengesha2015PlascitScintillators">Mengesha et al. (2015)</span>) This low energy resolution makes it difficult to distinguish gamma rays with closely spaced energies, which is common in the decay processes of many radionuclides.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Ely2008TheUse">Ely et al. (2008)</span>)</li>
<li>Compton Continuum and Absence of Distinct Photopeaks: The energy spectra obtained with plastic scintillators when exposed to gamma rays are dominated by a continuous energy distribution due to Compton scattering, lacking the distinct photopeaks (corresponding to the total energy of the incident gamma ray) that serve as unique identifiers for specific radionuclides in high-resolution detectors.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Ely2008TheUse">Ely et al. (2008)</span>)</li>
<li>Difficulty in Resolving Overlapping Energy Lines: In the case of samples containing mixed radionuclides, the broad spectral features from each nuclide, due to the low energy resolution, significantly overlap. This makes it very challenging to separate the contributions of individual isotopes and accurately identify all components within the mixture.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2020Evaluation">H. C. Lee et al. (2020)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Impact on accurate and reliable radionuclide identification:
<ul>
<li>Accurate radionuclide identification based solely on matching energy spectra to known gamma-ray energies (photopeaks) is nearly impossible for many radionuclides with plastic scintillators alone.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>In security applications, the inability to accurately identify radionuclides can lead to high false alarm rates caused by Naturally Occurring Radioactive Materials (NORM) that emit radiation with similar energies to targeted artificial sources.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2020Evaluation">H. C. Lee et al. (2020)</span>) These false alarms can cause operational disruptions and increase costs associated with secondary inspections.</li>
<li>Accurately quantifying the activity of individual radionuclides within a mixed source is severely hampered by the lack of distinct spectral features and the nature of the overlapping Compton continuum.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-2">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Insight 5</strong>: The inherent limitation of energy resolution exhibited by plastic scintillators acts as a significant barrier in applications requiring clear and unambiguous radionuclide identification. This necessitates the development of specialized techniques capable of extracting more identification information from the limited spectral data.
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: The physical processes governing the interaction of gamma rays with plastic scintillators (primarily Compton scattering) are fundamental and not easily altered. Therefore, advancements in radionuclide identification using these detectors must focus on sophisticated data processing and analysis methods to overcome these inherent physical limitations.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Insight 6</strong>: The practical consequences of low energy resolution, such as high false alarm rates in security monitoring and difficulties in quantifying mixed sources, highlight the urgent need for improved identification techniques. These challenges underscore the importance of research into advanced algorithms and detector designs that can enhance the analytical capabilities of plastic scintillators in real-world applications.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="radionuclide-identification-technologies-and-advancements-using-plastic-scintillators" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="radionuclide-identification-technologies-and-advancements-using-plastic-scintillators"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Radionuclide Identification Technologies and Advancements Using Plastic Scintillators:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Energy Spectroscopy and Its Limitations:
<ul>
<li>Basic Principle: Gamma-ray spectroscopy involves measuring the energy distribution of gamma rays emitted from a sample to identify the constituent radionuclides based on their unique energy emissions (observed as photopeaks in high-resolution spectra).<sup>21</sup></li>
<li>Limitations of Plastic Scintillators: Due to the dominance of Compton scattering and low energy resolution, the energy spectra obtained with plastic scintillators tend to lack the distinct photopeaks necessary for direct and clear radionuclide identification.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>) The spectra are dominated by the Compton continuum, a broad energy distribution of scattered photons.</li>
<li>Compton Edge Analysis: The Compton edge represents the maximum energy transferred to an electron in a Compton scattering event and can be determined in the spectrum, providing some information about the maximum energy of the incident gamma ray.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Kim2018EnergyResolution">Kim et al. (2018)</span>) However, the Compton edge energy is not unique to specific radionuclides, and its accurate determination is affected by the detector’s energy resolution, limiting its usefulness for definitive identification.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Pulse Shape Discrimination (PSD):
<ul>
<li>Principle: PSD is a technique that exploits subtle differences in the temporal shape of scintillation pulses generated by different types of radiation (e.g., gamma rays and neutrons) based on the rate of energy loss (dE/dx) within the scintillator material.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2024PulseShape">Y. Lee et al. (2024)</span>) Neutrons tend to produce pulses with a slower decay component compared to gamma rays due to their interaction with nuclei, while gamma rays primarily interact with electrons.</li>
<li>Key Applications: PSD is very effective in distinguishing neutron-induced signals from gamma-ray-induced signals in organic scintillators (including plastic) and is widely used in mixed radiation field measurements.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Pozzi2013PulseShape">Pozzi, Bourne, and Clarke (2013)</span>)</li>
<li>Limited Direct Use for Gamma Radionuclide Identification (Based on Plastic Scintillator Energy Spectra Alone): While PSD can differentiate between neutrons and gamma rays, the temporal pulse shapes generated by different gamma energies or different gamma-emitting radionuclides in plastic scintillators tend to be very similar. This makes it challenging to use PSD for detailed radionuclide identification within the gamma energy range based solely on the energy spectrum from a plastic scintillator.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Energy-Weighted Algorithms:
<ul>
<li>Principle: Energy-weighted algorithms aim to enhance the spectral information obtained from plastic scintillators by modifying the raw energy spectrum through the assignment of weights based on the energy of each channel. This often involves multiplying the count rate of each channel by an energy-related factor, particularly emphasizing the Compton maximum to make it appear as a more distinct and identifiable peak.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>Mathematical Formula: A common approach is to calculate the energy-weighted count (EWAi) for each channel (i) by multiplying the original count (Ci) by the energy coefficient (Ei) of that channel (EWAi=Ci×Ei).(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2016Validation">H. Lee et al. (2016)</span>) Various modifications have been investigated, such as introducing integer constants to optimize the algorithm for specific applications.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2020Evaluation">H. C. Lee et al. (2020)</span>)</li>
<li>Mechanism of Improvement: By emphasizing the Compton edge region, which is related to the maximum energy of the incident gamma ray, energy-weighted algorithms can help generate more characteristic spectral signatures for different radionuclides even with the low energy resolution of plastic scintillators.<sup>22</sup> This transformation can convert the gradual distribution of the Compton edge into a more conspicuous peak.</li>
<li>Validation Studies: Numerous studies have demonstrated the effectiveness of energy-weighted algorithms in enhancing the identification capabilities among various radionuclides, such as <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E%7B137%7D">Cs, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E%7B60%7D">Co, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E%7B22%7D">Na, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E%7B40%7D">K, using plastic scintillators in both laboratory experiments and real-world applications like Radiation Portal Monitors (RPMs).(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>) These algorithms have also shown potential in distinguishing artificial radionuclides from Naturally Occurring Radioactive Materials (NORM).<sup>23</sup></li>
<li>Limitations: The effectiveness of energy-weighted algorithms can be reduced when dealing with complex mixtures of radionuclides, especially if the Compton edges or energy-weighted peaks significantly overlap.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2020Evaluation">H. C. Lee et al. (2020)</span>) Performance can also be affected by factors such as shielding and the speed of moving sources in RPM applications.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Machine Learning Approaches:
<ul>
<li>Principle: Machine learning models, such as Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs), Artificial Neural Networks (ANNs), Support Vector Machines (SVMs), and Transformer-based networks, are increasingly being applied to recognize patterns and classify unknown spectra after being trained on large datasets of plastic scintillator spectra from known radionuclides.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>Data Preprocessing: Common techniques include removing background noise, normalizing the spectra to a consistent scale, and converting the one-dimensional spectral data into two-dimensional image representations for use as input to CNNs.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Istofa2025RadionuclideIdentification">Istofa et al. (2025)</span>)</li>
<li>Performance Evaluation: Studies using machine learning models trained on plastic scintillator spectra have reported high prediction accuracies (often exceeding 90% and reaching up to 98% under specific conditions) in identifying individual and mixed radionuclides.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>) These models have shown robustness in identifying radionuclides with similar Compton edge energies and under various challenging conditions such as dynamic source movement and the presence of shielding.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>Addressing Challenges: Machine learning approaches have shown the potential to overcome limitations such as low energy resolution and the absence of photopeaks. CNNs, in particular, are promising for extracting relevant features from spectral data through convolution and pooling operations.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Turner2021ConvolutionalNeuralNetwork">Turner et al. (2021)</span>)</li>
<li>Explainable AI (XAI): Recognizing that machine learning models, especially deep learning networks, are often considered “black boxes,” there is increasing interest in using XAI techniques to understand and interpret the decision-making processes in critical applications like radionuclide identification. Methods such as saliency mapping and Gradient-weighted Class Activation Mapping (Grad-CAM) are being investigated to identify which parts of the energy spectrum the models focus on when making classifications.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Jeon2023Explanation">Jeon, Kim, and and (2023)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Multi-Array Plastic Scintillator Detectors:
<ul>
<li>Principle: Instead of a single large-volume detector, using an array of multiple smaller plastic scintillators can improve the overall photon collection efficiency and potentially provide spatial information about the radiation source, which can aid in identification.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>Demonstrated Advantages: Multi-array detectors have been shown to have a higher probability of collecting optical photons generated within the scintillator compared to conventional single-element detectors.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>Combination with Algorithms: When combined with energy-weighted algorithms and machine learning models, multi-array systems have demonstrated enhanced performance in identifying moving radiation sources.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Hybrid Detection Systems:
<ul>
<li>Principle: Combining plastic scintillators with detectors that offer complementary strengths, such as high energy resolution (e.g., High-Purity Germanium - HPGe detectors), can enhance radionuclide identification capabilities. While plastic scintillators can provide high detection efficiency due to their large volume, HPGe detectors can offer precise energy measurements for clear identification, either through coincidence counting techniques or by analyzing a subset of events with high energy resolution.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Goodwin2023PlasticScintillator">Goodwin et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Advanced Scintillator Materials and Additives:
<ul>
<li>Ongoing research focuses on developing new plastic scintillator materials and incorporating specific compounds (e.g., organic tin) into the polymer matrix to enhance light yield, potentially improve energy resolution, and enable better pulse shape discrimination for spectroscopic applications.<sup>24</sup> This includes research on radiation-hardened plastics for use in harsh environments.</li>
<li>The development of hybrid plastic scintillators by mixing different polymers such as polystyrene and polymethylmethacrylate (PMMA) shows promise in improving optical transparency and mechanical durability, which could lead to more efficient and reliable detectors.<sup>25</sup></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-3">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Insight 7</strong>: Advancements in radionuclide identification technology using plastic scintillators are likely to occur through a synergistic effect combining progress in materials science, detector design, and computational intelligence. This suggests that progress will be made through incremental improvements across multiple research fields rather than a single revolutionary breakthrough.
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: The inherent physical limitations of plastic scintillators will likely not be completely overcome by material improvements alone. Integrating better materials with more sophisticated algorithms and detector configurations is the most promising way to significantly enhance the radionuclide identification capabilities of plastic scintillators.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Insight 8</strong>: The rise of machine learning and AI-based analysis suggests the potential for portable and field-deployable plastic scintillator systems to achieve levels of radionuclide identification accuracy previously attainable only with more sophisticated and less mobile detector technologies. This could have significant implications for various fields, especially in security and emergency response scenarios.
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: The ability of machine learning models to learn complex patterns from large datasets of spectral information offers a promising path to extract identification features not easily revealed by traditional analysis methods. This could lead to the development of highly effective radionuclide identification systems while maintaining portability and cost-effectiveness.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="comparison-with-other-radionuclide-identification-technologies" class="level2" data-number="5">
<h2 data-number="5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comparison-with-other-radionuclide-identification-technologies"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Comparison with Other Radionuclide Identification Technologies:</h2>
<div id="tbl-comparison_of_RIT" class="striped hover quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-comparison_of_RIT-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
표&nbsp;1: Comparison of Radionuclide Identification Technologies for Gamma-Ray Spectroscopy
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-comparison_of_RIT-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="table-striped table-hover caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 21%">
<col style="width: 26%">
<col style="width: 26%">
<col style="width: 26%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: center;">Feature</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Plastic Scintillator</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Inorganic Scintillator (NaI(Tl))</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Semiconductor Detector (HPGe)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Energy Resolution</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low (10-15% at 662 keV)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Medium (6-8% at 662 keV)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Excellent (&lt;1% at 662 keV)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Density</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Effective Atomic Number</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Cost</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Medium</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Portability</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High (lightweight, rugged)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Medium</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low (requires cooling)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Photopeak Presence</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Weak or absent due to Compton dominance</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Distinct</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Distinct</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Gamma-Ray Sensitivity</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Medium</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Neutron Sensitivity</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low (can be doped for thermal neutrons)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low (can be doped for thermal neutrons)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Sensitive to fast neutrons</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Response Speed</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Fast (nanoseconds)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Medium (microseconds)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Slow (microseconds)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Main Applications</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">RPM, high count rate environments, beta detection, wide area monitoring</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Medical imaging, general gamma-ray spectroscopy, field RIID</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High-resolution spectroscopy, low-level counting</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Radionuclide ID Ability</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Limited (requires advanced algorithms or hybrid systems)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Good (based on photopeaks)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Excellent (precise energy measurement)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Inorganic Scintillators (NaI(Tl), CsI(Tl), LaBr3):</strong> Offer significantly better energy resolution than plastic scintillators, allowing for more direct and reliable radionuclide identification through the analysis of characteristic photopeaks.<sup>26</sup><sup>,</sup> <sup>27</sup> For example, NaI(Tl) has high light yield and good resolution, making it suitable for radionuclide identification equipment.[9] LaBr3 scintillators offer even better resolution than NaI(Tl).<sup>28</sup> However, inorganic scintillators are generally more expensive, and some are hygroscopic, requiring careful handling and packaging.<sup>29</sup><sup>,</sup><sup>30</sup></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Semiconductor Detectors (HPGe, CZT):</strong> Provide the best energy resolution among commonly used radiation detectors, enabling very accurate identification of complex radionuclide mixtures and detection of low-activity sources.<sup>31</sup><sup>,</sup><sup>32</sup> HPGe detectors require cryogenic cooling for operation, limiting their portability and increasing operational complexity. CZT detectors can operate at room temperature but are generally more expensive than scintillators.<sup>33</sup><sup>,</sup> <sup>34</sup></p></li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-4">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Insight 9:</strong> The choice of detector technology for radionuclide identification involves a trade-off between performance characteristics like energy resolution and detection efficiency, and practical considerations such as cost, portability, and operational complexity. Plastic scintillators offer advantages in cost, size, and speed, albeit with some sacrifice in spectroscopic accuracy, making them suitable for scenarios where these factors are paramount.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought:</strong> High-throughput screening at ports (RPMs) favors plastic scintillators over costly high-resolution detectors, while laboratory environments for environmental monitoring might prioritize the high resolution of HPGe detectors to accurately identify trace amounts of radionuclides.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Insight 10:</strong> The development of hybrid systems combining plastic scintillators with other detector types represents an effort to leverage the complementary strengths of different technologies. This approach recognizes that no single detector is ideal for all scenarios and aims to create more versatile and high-performance solutions for radionuclide identification.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="examples-of-portable-and-field-deployable-systems" class="level2" data-number="6">
<h2 data-number="6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="examples-of-portable-and-field-deployable-systems"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> Examples of Portable and Field-Deployable Systems:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Radiation Portal Monitors (RPMs): Commonly use large-volume plastic scintillators for primary screening.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>) Often combined with energy-weighted algorithms and machine learning for enhanced (though still limited) identification capabilities.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>Portable Radionuclide Identification Devices (RIIDs): Many handheld RIIDs designed for first responders, law enforcement, and security personnel incorporate plastic scintillators to balance sensitivity, fast response, and ruggedness for field use.<sup>35</sup> These devices often include algorithms that provide some level of radionuclide identification based on the acquired spectra.</li>
<li>Wearable Personal Radiation Dosimeters: Small plastic scintillators coupled with SiPMs are being developed for real-time monitoring of personal radiation exposure.<sup>36</sup> While primarily for dose measurement, some advanced models may offer basic radionuclide identification features.</li>
<li>Backpack Radiation Detection Systems: Portable systems designed for searching for radiation sources over large areas may include plastic scintillators for gamma and neutron detection.<sup>37</sup> These systems often incorporate software for data analysis and potential isotope identification.</li>
<li>Plastic Scintillation Optical Fiber (PSOF) Detectors: These flexible and long detectors can be deployed in the field for radiation monitoring in contaminated areas and liquid environments, offering flexibility and extended reach.[^27] When coupled with appropriate analysis techniques, they can provide information on the presence of specific radionuclides.</li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-5" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-5">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications:</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Insight 11</strong>: The development of various portable systems based on plastic scintillators demonstrates the ongoing need for field-deployable solutions for radionuclide detection and identification, particularly in security and emergency response scenarios. In these scenarios, the advantages of plastic scintillators (size, weight, cost) often outweigh their spectroscopic limitations.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: The increasing threat of nuclear and radiological terrorism and the need for rapid environmental monitoring in case of accidents drive the demand for easily transportable and user-friendly detection systems. Plastic scintillators, easily integrated into such systems, play a crucial role in addressing these needs.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="recent-advancements-and-future-trends" class="level2" data-number="7">
<h2 data-number="7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recent-advancements-and-future-trends"><span class="header-section-number">7</span> Recent Advancements and Future Trends:</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Continued development and improvement of energy-weighted algorithms and machine learning models (including deep learning architectures) to enhance the identification capabilities of plastic scintillators.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>) Focus on improving accuracy, handling complex mixtures, and reducing false alarm rates.</p></li>
<li><p>Research into new plastic scintillator materials incorporating novel organic compounds or heavy metal additives to enhance light yield and potentially improve energy resolution and enable better pulse shape discrimination for spectroscopy.<sup>38</sup> Includes development of radiation-hardened plastics for use in harsh environments.</p></li>
<li><p>Advancements in photosensor technology, particularly SiPMs, offering the potential to make portable systems even smaller, more rugged, and power-efficient.<sup>39</sup></p></li>
<li><p>Research into hybrid detector designs combining plastic scintillators with other types of detectors to achieve a balance of high efficiency and good energy resolution.</p></li>
<li><p>Development of more sophisticated signal processing techniques to extract additional information from scintillation pulses and potentially improve the identification of different radionuclides.</p></li>
<li><p>Increasing interest in the explainability and interpretability of machine learning models used for radionuclide identification in critical applications.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Jeon2023Explanation">Jeon, Kim, and and (2023)</span>)</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-6" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-6">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Insight 12</strong>: The future of radionuclide identification using plastic scintillators will likely depend heavily on the convergence of advancements in materials science, detector engineering, and computational intelligence. This suggests that progress will be made through incremental improvements across multiple research fields rather than a single revolutionary breakthrough.
<ul>
<li>Chain of Thought: The inherent physical limitations of plastic scintillators will likely not be completely overcome by material improvements alone. Integrating better materials with more sophisticated algorithms and detector configurations is the most promising way to significantly enhance the radionuclide identification capabilities of plastic scintillators.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Insight 13</strong>: The rise of machine learning and AI-based analysis suggests the potential for portable and field-deployable plastic scintillator systems to achieve levels of radionuclide identification accuracy previously attainable only with more sophisticated and less mobile detector technologies. This could have significant implications for various fields, especially in security and emergency response scenarios.
<ul>
<li>Chain of Thought: The ability of machine learning models to learn complex patterns from large datasets of spectral information offers a promising path to extract identification features not easily revealed by traditional analysis methods. This could lead to the development of highly effective radionuclide identification systems while maintaining portability and cost-effectiveness.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2" data-number="8">
<h2 data-number="8" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion"><span class="header-section-number">8</span> Conclusion:</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Summary of current capabilities and limitations of radionuclide identification using plastic scintillators: Offers advantages in cost-effectiveness, speed, and portability, but low energy resolution poses significant challenges for accurate radionuclide identification.</p></li>
<li><p>Summary of advancements: The application of energy-weighted algorithms and machine learning techniques has led to significant progress in extracting more identification information from limited spectral data. Multi-array and hybrid detector designs also show potential for improved performance.</p></li>
<li><p>Future outlook: Continued research into advanced materials, innovative detector designs, and sophisticated computational methods is likely to further advance this field. While plastic scintillators may not completely replace high-resolution detectors in all applications, ongoing innovation is expected to expand their role in radionuclide identification, especially in scenarios where their unique advantages are crucial, such as portable and field-deployable systems.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
<section id="references" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h3>
<div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-Ely2008TheUse" class="csl-entry">
Ely, James, Kevin Anderson, Derrick Bates, Richard Kouzes, C. Presti, Robert Runkle, Edward Siciliano, and Dennis Weier. 2008. <span>‘The Use of Energy Information in Plastic Scintillator Material’</span>. <em>Journal of Radioanalytical and Nuclear Chemistry - J RADIOANAL NUCL CHEM</em> 276 (June): 743–48. https://doi.org/<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10967-008-0627-5">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10967-008-0627-5</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Goodwin2023PlasticScintillator" class="csl-entry">
Goodwin, M A, T P Gill, A V Davies, R Britton, S J Bell, and P H Regan. 2023. <span>‘A Plastic Scintillator and HPGe β-Γcoincidence Detection System.’</span> <em>Appl Radiat Isot</em> 201 (November): 111028. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apradiso.2023.111028">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apradiso.2023.111028</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Istofa2025RadionuclideIdentification" class="csl-entry">
Istofa, Istofa, Gina Kusuma, Firliyani Ningsih, Joko Triyanto, I Putu Susila, and Prawito Prajitno. 2025. <span>‘Radionuclide Identification System Using Convolution Neural Network for Environmental Radiation Monitoring’</span>. <em>International Journal of Electrical and Computer Engineering (IJECE)</em> 15 (April): 2282. <a href="https://doi.org/10.11591/ijece.v15i2.pp2282-2290">https://doi.org/10.11591/ijece.v15i2.pp2282-2290</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jeon2023Explanation" class="csl-entry">
Jeon, Byoungil, Jinhwan Kim, and Myungkook Moon and. 2023. <span>‘Explanation of Deep Learning–Based Radioisotope Identifier for Plastic Scintillation Detector’</span>. <em>Nuclear Technology</em> 209 (1): 1–14. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/00295450.2022.2096389">https://doi.org/10.1080/00295450.2022.2096389</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Kim2018EnergyResolution" class="csl-entry">
Kim, Yonghyun, Jaebum Son, Junesic Park, Dong-geon Kim, Kihong Pak Pak, Sangmin Lee, and Yong Kyun Kim. 2018. <span>‘Energy Resolution of the Fabricated Plastic Scintillator’</span>. Korean Nuclear Society; Korean Nuclear Society.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lee2020Evaluation" class="csl-entry">
Lee, Hyun Cheol, Bon Tack Koo, Chang Il Choi, Chang Su Park, Jeongwan Kwon, Hong-Suk Kim, Heejun Chung, and Min Chul Hee. 2020. <span>‘Evaluation of Source Identification Method Based on Energy-Weighting Level with Portal Monitoring System Using Plastic Scintillator’</span>. <em>J. Radiat. Prot. Res</em> 45 (3): 117–29. <a href="https://doi.org/10.14407/jrpr.2020.45.3.117">https://doi.org/10.14407/jrpr.2020.45.3.117</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lee2023Radionuclide" class="csl-entry">
Lee, Hyun Cheol, Bon Tack Koo, Ju Young Jeon, Bo-Wi Cheon, Do Hyeon Yoo, Heejun Chung, and Chul Hee Min. 2023. <span>‘Radionuclide Identification Based on Energy-Weighted Algorithm and Machine Learning Applied to a Multi-Array Plastic Scintillator’</span>. <em>Nuclear Engineering and Technology</em> 55 (10): 3907–12. https://doi.org/<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.net.2023.07.005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.net.2023.07.005</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lee2016Validation" class="csl-entry">
Lee, Hyun, Wook-Geun Shin, Hyo Park, Dohyeon Yoo, Chang-Il Choi, Chang-Su Park, Hong-Suk Kim, and Chul Hee Min. 2016. <span>‘Validation of Energy-Weighted Algorithm for Radiation Portal Monitor Using Plastic Scintillator’</span>. <em>Applied Radiation and Isotopes</em> 107 (January): 160–64. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apradiso.2015.10.019">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apradiso.2015.10.019</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lee2024PulseShape" class="csl-entry">
Lee, Yujin, Jinyoung Kim, Byoung-cheol Koh, Young Soo Yoon, and Chang Hyon Ha. 2024. <span>‘Pulse Shape Discrimination in an Organic Scintillation Phoswich Detector Using Machine Learning Techniques’</span>. <em>Frontiers in Physics</em> Volume 12 - 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphy.2024.1361608">https://doi.org/10.3389/fphy.2024.1361608</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mengesha2015PlascitScintillators" class="csl-entry">
Mengesha, Wondwosen, Patrick L Feng, Joseph Gabriel Cordaro, Mitchell Anstey, Nicholas Myllenbeck, and Daniel J. Throckmorton. 2015. <span>‘Plastic Scintillators Light Yield Energy Calibration.’</span>, December. <a href="https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1427195">https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1427195</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Pozzi2013PulseShape" class="csl-entry">
Pozzi, Sara, Mark Bourne, and Shaun Clarke. 2013. <span>‘Pulse Shape Discrimination in the Plastic Scintillator EJ-299-33’</span>. <em>Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section A: Accelerators, Spectrometers, Detectors and Associated Equipment</em> 723 (September): 19–23. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nima.2013.04.085">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nima.2013.04.085</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Turner2021ConvolutionalNeuralNetwork" class="csl-entry">
Turner, Anthony, Carl Wheldon, Tzany Kokalova Wheldon, Mark Gilbert, Lee Packer, Jonathan Burns, and Martin Freer. 2021. <span>‘Convolutional Neural Networks for Challenges in Automated Nuclide Identification’</span>. <em>Sensors</em> 21 (August): 5238. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/s21155238">https://doi.org/10.3390/s21155238</a>.
</div>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="참고자료" class="level2" data-number="9">
<h2 data-number="9" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="참고자료"><span class="header-section-number">9</span> 참고자료</h2>
<p>[2] Feasibility study for radionuclide identification using multi-array …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/338055509_Feasibility_study_for_radionuclide_identification_using_multi-array_plastic_scintillator_and_energy_weighted_algorithm_of_radiation_portal_monitors_a_Monte_Carlo_study</p>
<p>[3] Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/</p>
<p>[4] Scintillator - Wikipedia, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scintillator</p>
<p>[5] SB 40/150 Plastic Scintillators - Mirion Technologies, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.mirion.com/products/technologies/radiation-monitoring-systems/pro-tk-radiation-and-process-monitoring-systems/radiation-detectors-1e/sb-40-150-plastic-scintillators</p>
<p>[6] Plastic Scintillators | Oncology Medical Physics, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://oncologymedicalphysics.com/plastic-scintillators/</p>
<p>[7] Scintillation Detectors ⋆ Scionix, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://scionix.nl/scintillation-detectors/</p>
<p>[8] Scintillators - OSTI, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1867988</p>
<p>[9] Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors</p>
<p>[10] Scintillators!, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.oeaw.ac.at/fileadmin/Institute/HEPHY/PDF/ausbildung/praktikum/VO-5-Scintillators.pdf</p>
<p>[11] Energy resolution of plastic scintillation detector for beta rays, H. H. Vo et. al.&nbsp;<em>IEEE Transactions on Nuclear Science</em>, <strong>55</strong> (6):3717-3724, 2008 DOI: 10.1109/TNS.2008.2005718, https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/4723822</p>
<p>[12] Unlocking the Secrets of Radiation: Marvel of the Scintillation Counter - Open MedScience, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://openmedscience.com/unlocking-the-secrets-of-radiation-marvel-of-the-scintillation-counter/</p>
<p>[16] Silicon Photomultiplier (SiPM) Readout of Scintillators | Berkeley …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/silicon-photomultiplier-readout</p>
<p>[17] Scintillation detector with SiPM matrix as a photosensor | Request PDF, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/322680188_Scintillation_detector_with_SiPM_matrix_as_a_photosensor</p>
<p>[20] PULSE SHAPE DISCRIMINATION IN A PLASTIC SCINTILLATOR (Journal Article) - OSTI, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.osti.gov/biblio/4140599</p>
<p>[21] EJ-276D - Pulse Shape Discrimination Plastic Scintillator - Eljen Technology, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://eljentechnology.com/products/plastic-scintillators/ej-276</p>
<p>[22] Pulse shape simulations for organic scintillation detectors using Geant4 - EPJ Web of Conferences, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.epj-conferences.org/articles/epjconf/pdf/2021/07/epjconf_animma2021_11002.pdf</p>
<p>[23] Validation of energy-weighted algorithm for radiation portal monitor using plastic scintillator, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/283844276_Validation_of_energy-weighted_algorithm_for_radiation_portal_monitor_using_plastic_scintillator</p>
<p>[25] A Monte Carlo study of an energy-weighted algorithm for radionuclide analysis with a plastic scintillation detector - ResearchGate, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/274397333_A_Monte_Carlo_study_of_an_energy-weighted_algorithm_for_radionuclide_analysis_with_a_plastic_scintillation_detector</p>
<p>[28] Development of a radionuclide identification algorithm based on a convolutional neural network for radiation portal monitoring system - INIS-IAEA, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://inis.iaea.org/records/cdxny-y9z44</p>
<p>[29] Comparison of Machine Learning-Based Radioisotope Identifiers for Plastic Scintillation Detector - Korea Science, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://koreascience.kr/article/JAKO202108458484352.page</p>
<p>[30] Comparison of Machine Learning-Based Radioisotope Identifiers for Plastic Scintillation Detector - Journal of Radiation Protection and Research, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.jrpr.org/include/download.php?filedata=1098%7Cjrpr-2021-00206.pdf</p>
<p>[34] Explaining machine-learning models for gamma-ray detection and identification - PMC, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10281578/</p>
<p>[35] Explaining machine-learning models for gamma-ray detection and identification | PLOS One, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0286829</p>
<p>[36] Pseudo-Gamma Spectroscopy Based on Plastic Scintillation Detectors Using Multitask Learning - MDPI, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/21/3/684</p>
<p>[40] Data Support of Generalization Ability of a CNN γ-ray Localization Model for Radiation Imaging, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.scidb.cn/en/detail?dataSetId=4ba07b2a777743d8938e920c3c258815</p>
<p>[43] Plastic Scintillators Light Yield Energy Calibration - OSTI, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1427195</p>
<p>[44] Hybrid plastic scintillators aim to improve nuclear safety and medical imaging - EurekAlert!, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/1068785</p>
<p>[45] Recent developments in plastic scintillators with pulse shape discrimination - ResearchGate, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/322877963_Recent_developments_in_plastic_scintillators_with_pulse_shape_discrimination</p>
<p>[46] Current status on plastic scintillators modifications (Conference) | OSTI.GOV, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.osti.gov/biblio/22531431</p>
<p>[47] Synthesis and Analysis of Novel Materials for Plastic Scintillators - eScholarship, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://escholarship.org/content/qt195786t5/qt195786t5.pdf?t=orl5aa</p>
<p>[48] Scintillation Radiation Detectors | Berkeley Nucleonics®, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/scintillation-crystals-detectors</p>
<p>[49] SAM 940 (RIID) Handheld Radiation Isotope Identifier - Berkeley Nucleonics, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/sam-940-riid</p>
<p>[50] RADEAGLET-R Rugged, Lightweight, Handheld Radioisotope Identification Device, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.ortec-online.com/products/portable-radioisotope-identification-devices-riids/radeaglet-r</p>
<p>[51] js-techwin.com, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://js-techwin.com/data/file/brochure/Products-JSTECHWIN%20(eng).pdf</p>
<p>[52] Portable Radiation Instruments - Handheld | LAURUS Systems, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.laurussystems.com/product-listing/handheld-radiation-instruments/</p>
<p>[53] Acquiring Gamma-Ray Energy Spectrum Using a Plastic Scintillation Optical Fiber Detector, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.mdpi.com/2304-6732/11/6/493</p>
<p>(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2016Validation">H. Lee et al. (2016)</span>): Validation of energy-weighted algorithm for radiation portal monitor using plastic scintillator, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/283844276_Validation_of_energy-weighted_algorithm_for_radiation_portal_monitor_using_plastic_scintillator</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">각주</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Scintillator - Wikipedia, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scintillator↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Scintillation Detectors ⋆ Scionix, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://scionix.nl/scintillation-detectors/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Scintillation Detectors ⋆ Scionix, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://scionix.nl/scintillation-detectors/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>Scintillator - Wikipedia, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scintillator↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn8"><p>Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn9"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn10"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn11"><p>Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn12"><p>Scintillator - Wikipedia, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scintillator↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn13"><p>Scintillator - Wikipedia, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scintillator↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn14"><p>Scintillators!, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.oeaw.ac.at/fileadmin/Institute/HEPHY/PDF/ausbildung/praktikum/VO-5-Scintillators.pdf↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn15"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn16"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn17"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn18"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn19"><p>Silicon Photomultiplier (SiPM) Readout of Scintillators | Berkeley …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/silicon-photomultiplier-readout↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn20"><p>Silicon Photomultiplier (SiPM) Readout of Scintillators | Berkeley …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/silicon-photomultiplier-readout↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn21"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn22"><p>Feasibility study for radionuclide identification using multi-array …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/338055509_Feasibility_study_for_radionuclide_identification_using_multi-array_plastic_scintillator_and_energy_weighted_algorithm_of_radiation_portal_monitors_a_Monte_Carlo_study↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn23"><p>Feasibility study for radionuclide identification using multi-array …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/338055509_Feasibility_study_for_radionuclide_identification_using_multi-array_plastic_scintillator_and_energy_weighted_algorithm_of_radiation_portal_monitors_a_Monte_Carlo_study↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn24"><p>Scintillators - OSTI, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1867988↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn25"><p>Optical transmittance and pulse shape discrimination of polystyrene/poly(methyl methacrylate)-based plastic scintillators - EurekAlert!, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/1068785↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn26"><p>Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn27"><p>Scintillation Radiation Detectors | Berkeley Nucleonics®, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/scintillation-crystals-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn28"><p>Scintillation Radiation Detectors | Berkeley Nucleonics®, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/scintillation-crystals-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn29"><p>Scintillators!, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.oeaw.ac.at/fileadmin/Institute/HEPHY/PDF/ausbildung/praktikum/VO-5-Scintillators.pdf↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn30"><p>Scintillation Radiation Detectors | Berkeley Nucleonics®, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/scintillation-crystals-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn31"><p>Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn32"><p>Scintillation Radiation Detectors | Berkeley Nucleonics®, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/scintillation-crystals-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn33"><p>Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn34"><p>Scintillation Radiation Detectors | Berkeley Nucleonics®, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/scintillation-crystals-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn35"><p>SAM 940 (RIID) Handheld Radiation Isotope Identifier - Berkeley Nucleonics, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/sam-940-riid↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn36"><p>js-techwin.com, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://js-techwin.com/data/file/brochure/Products-JSTECHWIN%20(eng).pdf↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn37"><p>Portable Radiation Instruments - Handheld | LAURUS Systems, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.laurussystems.com/product-listing/handheld-radiation-instruments/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn38"><p>Scintillators - OSTI, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1867988↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn39"><p>Silicon Photomultiplier (SiPM) Readout of Scintillators | Berkeley …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/silicon-photomultiplier-readout↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://julia-kaeri.github.io/src/posts/plastic_scintillator_eng.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 12:31:30 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>플라스틱 섬광체를 이용한 방사성 핵종 식별 기술 보고서</title>
  <dc:creator>Julia_KAERI</dc:creator>
  <link>https://julia-kaeri.github.io/src/posts/plastic_scintillator_kor.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
노트
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li><p><a href="../../src/posts/plastic_scintillator_eng.html">Report on Plastic Scintillator Radionuclide Identification Technology</a> 의 한글 번역 버젼으로 역시 google research 에 의해 생성되었음</p></li>
<li><p>이후 자료 보충함.</p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<p><br></p>
<section id="서론" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="서론"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> 서론:</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>핵종 식별 기술은 핵 안전, 핵 안보, 환경 감시, 의료 응용 등 다양한 분야에서 중요한 역할을 수행합니다. 특히 불법적인 핵 물질 거래를 방지하고 방사능 오염을 감시하는 데 필수적입니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>) 의료 분야에서는 핵의학 진단 및 치료에 사용되는 방사성 동위원소를 정확하게 식별하고 관리하는 데 중요합니다.<sup>1</sup> 산업 현장에서도 공정 제어 및 안전 관리를 위해 핵종 식별 기술이 활용됩니다.</p></li>
<li><p>플라스틱 섬광체 기반 방사선 검출기는 방사선 계측 분야에서 널리 사용되는 기술 중 하나입니다.</p>
<ul>
<li>플라스틱 섬광체는 플라스틱 기질과 형광 물질(fluor)로 구성되어 있으며.<sup>2</sup> 방사선이 플라스틱 섬광체에 입사하면 섬광 현상을 통해 방사선의 에너지를 가시광선 또는 근자외선 영역의 빛으로 변환합니다.<sup>3</sup></li>
<li>플라스틱 섬광체 검출기는 비용 효율성이 높고<sup>4</sup>, 응답 속도가 빠르며<sup>5</sup>, 다양한 형태로 제작이 용이하고<sup>6</sup>, 휴대용 기기에 적합한 견고성을 갖는다는 장점이 있습니다.<sup>7</sup></li>
<li>이러한 장점 덕분에 방사선 감시 장치, 휴대용 선량계, 그리고 방사선 물질 불법 거래 방지를 위한 방사선 감시 시스템(Radiation Portal Monitors, RPMs) 등 다양한 응용 분야에서 널리 사용되고 있습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>문제점 제시: 플라스틱 섬광체 기반 검출기는 감마선 에너지 분해능이 낮아 정확하고 신뢰성 있는 핵종 식별에 어려움이 있습니다. 이는 주로 콤프턴 산란이 주된 감마선 상호작용 메커니즘이기 때문이며, 섬광체 자체의 낮은 에너지 분해능 특성에도 기인합니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</p></li>
<li><p>보고서의 범위 및 목표: 본 보고서는 플라스틱 섬광체를 이용한 방사성 핵종 식별 기술의 원리, 한계점, 그리고 에너지 가중 알고리즘 및 머신러닝 접근법을 포함한 다양한 기술과 최근 발전 사항을 상세히 분석하고, 플라스틱 섬광체의 고유한 한계를 극복하고 핵종 식별 능력을 향상시키기 위한 혁신적인 해결책을 강조하는 것을 목표로 합니다.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications:</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Insight 1</strong>: 낮은 에너지 분해능에도 불구하고 RPM과 같은 분야에서 플라스틱 섬광체가 널리 사용되는 것은 성능(에너지 분해능)과 비용, 속도, 견고성과 같은 다른 요소 간의 절충을 시사합니다. 이러한 요소들은 보안 검색과 같이 많은 실제 응용 분야에서 매우 중요합니다.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong> : 플라스틱 섬광체는 저렴하고 취급이 용이하여 비용이 중요한 대규모 배치(예: RPM)에 이상적입니다. 빠른 응답 시간은 움직이는 물체를 신속하게 검사하는 데 중요합니다. 그러나 핵종을 정확하게 식별할 수 없다는 단점은 대체 기술 또는 보완 기술 개발의 필요성을 야기합니다.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Insight 2</strong>: 머신러닝 및 고급 알고리즘에 대한 관심 증가는 플라스틱 섬광체가 제공하는 제한된 스펙트럼 데이터에서 더 많은 정보를 추출하여 검출기 재료 자체의 물리적 한계를 극복하려는 강력한 노력을 나타냅니다. 이는 과학 기기에 데이터 과학의 발전이 광범위하게 적용되는 추세를 반영합니다.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: 플라스틱 섬광체의 고유한 에너지 분해능을 향상시키는 것은 어렵기 때문에 연구자들은 계산 방법을 통해 분석 능력을 향상시키는 데 주력하고 있습니다. 이러한 추세는 방사선 검출 분야에서 소프트웨어 기반 솔루션의 중요성이 커지고 있음을 보여줍니다.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="플라스틱-섬광체-방사선-검출기의-작동-원리" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="플라스틱-섬광체-방사선-검출기의-작동-원리"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> 플라스틱 섬광체 방사선 검출기의 작동 원리:</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>섬광 메커니즘: 방사선(핵종 식별의 경우 주로 감마선)이 플라스틱 섬광체 물질과 상호작용하면 분자를 여기시킵니다.<sup>8</sup></p>
<ul>
<li>여기된 에너지는 형광 물질(fluor)로 전달됩니다. 형광 물질은 플라스틱 내부에 도핑된 유기 형광 화합물(예: 안트라센(anthracene) 또는 비스-메틸스티렌(bis-methylstyrene))로 섬광 특성을 향상시킵니다.<sup>9</sup></li>
<li>여기된 형광 물질 분자는 바닥 상태로 되돌아가면서 가시광선 또는 근자외선 영역의 광자를 방출합니다.<sup>10</sup> 이 빛의 섬광이 섬광 현상입니다.</li>
<li>방출되는 빛의 강도는 입사 방사선의 에너지에 비례합니다.<sup>11</sup></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>에너지 분광학과 관련된 주요 특징:</p>
<ul>
<li>광 수율(Light yield): 단위 에너지당 생성되는 광자 수(일반적으로 NaI(Tl)과 같은 무기 섬광체에 비해 낮음).<sup>12</sup></li>
<li>섬광 효율(Scintillation efficiency): 입사 방사선의 운동 에너지를 검출 가능한 빛으로 변환하는 효율성.<sup>13</sup></li>
<li>감쇠 시간(Decay time): 일반적으로 매우 짧음(2-4 나노초)<sup>14</sup> 으로 빠른 검출 및 높은 계수율에 적합합니다<sup>15</sup></li>
<li>밀도 및 유효 원자 번호(Effective atomic number): 낮음(주로 탄소와 수소로 구성)으로 감마선에 대한 주된 상호작용 메커니즘은 콤프턴 산란입니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Ely2008TheUse">Ely et al. (2008)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>감마선의 주된 상호작용 메커니즘:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>콤프턴 산란(Compton scattering)</strong>: 입사 감마선이 원자의 전하와 상호작용하여 일부 에너지를 전자에 전달하고 산란되는 현상입니다.<sup>16</sup> 플라스틱 섬광체에서 주로 발생하며, 입사 감마선의 에너지에서 최소 에너지(콤프턴 엣지에 의해 결정됨)까지 연속적인 에너지 스펙트럼을 생성합니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Ely2008TheUse">Ely et al. (2008)</span>)</li>
<li><strong>광전 효과(Photoelectric effect)</strong>: 감마선이 원자에 완전히 흡수되어 궤도 전자를 방출하는 현상입니다(낮은 감마선 에너지 및 높은 원자 번호의 물질에서 더 잘 발생하며 플라스틱 섬광체에서는 덜 중요함).<sup>17</sup>. <u>이 경우 에너지가 물질 내에 흡수되며 검출 물질의 반응은 소위 <strong>full-energy peak</strong> 라고 불립니다(<span class="citation" data-cites="Ely2008TheUse">Ely et al. (2008)</span>).</u></li>
<li><strong>전자-양전자 쌍 생성(Pair production)</strong>: 감마선이 원자핵 근처에서 전자와 양전자 쌍으로 변환되는 현상입니다(감마선 에너지가 1.022 MeV를 초과할 때만 발생하며, 많은 일반적인 핵종 검출 응용 분야에서는 덜 중요함).<sup>18</sup></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>지배적 매커니즘과 검출기 물질(<span class="citation" data-cites="Ely2008TheUse">Ely et al. (2008)</span>):</p>
<ul>
<li>광전 흡수 메커니즘은 낮은 감마선 에너지에서 지배적인 반면, 컴프턴 산란은 더 높은 에너지에서 우세해지며, 그 이후에는 쌍생성(pair production)이 중요한 효과로 나타납니다. 광전 효과와 컴프턴 산란 중 어느 쪽이 지배적인지를 결정하는 주요 요인은 물질의 원자 번호(<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Z">)입니다.</li>
<li>플라스틱 신틸레이터(plastic scintillator) 같은 낮은 원자번호 물질에서는 광전 효과가 매우 낮은 에너지(50 keV 이하)에서만 지배적입니다. 반면, 탈륨이 첨가된 아이오딘화나트륨(<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BNaI(Tl)%7D">)처럼 원자번호가 높은 물질에서는 수백 keV에 이르는 에너지 범위까지도 광전 효과가 지배적입니다.</li>
<li>단일 상호작용 외에도, 일부 물질에서는 다중 컴프턴 산란(multiple Compton scattering)이 중요한 역할을 할 수 있습니다. 평균 자유 경로 길이(mean free path length)는 물질의 원자 번호(<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Z">)에 따라 달라지며, 원자 번호가 높은 물질일수록 동일한 부피 내에서 더 많은 상호작용이 발생합니다. 다중 산란은 단일 컴프턴 상호작용만으로는 불가능한 더 많은 총 에너지 침전(deposition)을 가능하게 하는 메커니즘을 제공합니다. 또한, 원자 번호가 높은 물질에서는 첫 번째 컴프턴 산란에서 충분한 에너지가 침전되어 이후 광전 효과가 두 번째 상호작용으로 일어날 수 있습니다. 이러한 방식으로, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BNaI(Tl)%7D">과 같은 일부 검출기 물질에서는 관심 에너지 영역 전반에 걸쳐 전 에너지 피크(full energy peaks)를 관측할 수 있습니다.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>광센서의 역할:</p>
<ul>
<li>광전자 증배관(Photomultiplier Tubes, PMTs): 섬광체에서 방출되는 미약한 빛을 감지하여 전기 신호로 변환하고 증폭하는 진공 기반 장치로, 광음극에서 광전 효과를 통해 전자를 방출하고 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynode">다이노드</a>에서 전자 증폭을 수행합니다.<sup>19</sup> 작동을 위해 고전압 전원 공급 장치가 필요합니다.<sup>20</sup></li>
<li>실리콘 광증배관(Silicon Photomultipliers, SiPMs): 고체 상태의 광센서로, 소형, 저전압 작동, 자기장에 대한 불감응성과 같은 장점을 제공하여 휴대용 응용 분야에서 PMT의 대안으로 점점 더 많이 사용되고 있습니다.<sup>21</sup> 일부 시나리오에서는 PMT와 비슷한 에너지 분해능을 달성할 수 있습니다.<sup>22</sup></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-1">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Insight 3</strong>: <u>플라스틱 섬광체의 낮은 유효 원자 번호로 인해 감마선과의 주된 상호작용은 콤프턴 산란이며</u>, 이는 고분해능 에너지 분광학과 직접적인 핵종 식별에 필요한 이산적인 에너지 정보를 얻는 데 근본적인 제약을 가합니다.
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: 광전 흡수, 즉 원하는 완전 에너지 피크를 유도하는 과정의 확률은 검출기 물질의 원자 번호에 크게 의존합니다. 플라스틱 섬광체를 구성하는 원소는 주로 탄소와 수소같은 낮은 원자번호를 가지며 이는 콤프턴 산란이 주된 과정임을 의미하며 결과적으로 명확한 핵종 식별에 필요한 개별 피크보다는 연속적인 에너지 스펙트럼을 얻게됩니다.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Insight 4</strong>: 광센서(PMT 또는 SiPM)의 선택은 감도, 전력 소비, 다양한 환경(예: 자기장 존재)에 대한 적합성과 같은 검출기 시스템의 전반적인 성능에 영향을 미칠 수 있지만, 섬광체 물질 자체에 의해 부과되는 에너지 분해능의 근본적인 한계는 변경되지 않습니다. 광센서의 주요 역할은 섬광체에서 생성된 빛을 전기 신호로 효율적으로 변환하는 것입니다. 초기 감마선 상호작용의 물리학에 의해 제한되는 빛의 정보 내용은 사용된 광센서에 관계없이 동일하게 유지됩니다.
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: 사고의 흐름: PMT와 SiPM 모두 플라스틱 섬광체에서 나오는 미약한 빛을 감지할 수 있습니다. SiPM은 크기와 작동 특성으로 인해 특정 응용 분야에서 장점을 제공하지만, 플라스틱에서 생성된 섬광(scintillation light)은 콤프턴 산란 사건의 결과이며, 이는 본질적으로 에너지 스펙트럼을 넓히고 개별 핵종의 고유한 에너지 특징을 가립니다.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="플라스틱-섬광체를-이용한-핵종-식별의-어려움" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="플라스틱-섬광체를-이용한-핵종-식별의-어려움"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> 플라스틱 섬광체를 이용한 핵종 식별의 어려움:</h2>
<ul>
<li>정확한 핵종 식별을 저해하는 고유한 한계점에 대한 상세 논의:
<ul>
<li>낮은 에너지 분해능: 일반적으로 662 keV(<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E%7B137%7D%20%5Ctext%7BCs%7D">)에서 10-15% 수준으로(<span class="citation" data-cites="Mengesha2015PlascitScintillators">Mengesha et al. (2015)</span>), <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BNaI(Tl)%7D">(6-8%)(<span class="citation" data-cites="Persyk1978StateOfTheArt">Persyk and Moi (1978)</span>) 과 같은 무기 섬광체나 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BHPGe%7D"> 검출기(&lt;1%)(<span class="citation" data-cites="Hafzoglu2024Efficiency">Hafızoğlu (2024)</span>) 에 비해 현저히 낮습니다. 이처럼 낮은 에너지 분해능은 에너지 간격이 좁은 감마선을 구별하기 어렵게 만듭니다. 이는 많은 핵종의 붕괴 과정에서 흔히 발생합니다.</li>
<li>콤프턴 연속 스펙트럼 및 뚜렷한 광전 피크의 부재: 플라스틱 섬광체가 감마선에 노출될 때 얻는 에너지 스펙트럼은 콤프턴 산란으로 인한 연속적인 에너지 분포가 주를 이루며, 고분해능 검출기에서 특정 핵종의 고유한 식별자로 작용하는 뚜렷한 광전 피크(입사 감마선의 총 에너지에 해당)가 부족합니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Ely2008TheUse">Ely et al. (2008)</span>)</li>
<li>겹치는 에너지 선 분해의 어려움: 혼합 핵종을 포함하는 시료의 경우, 낮은 에너지 분해능으로 인해 각 핵종에서 방출되는 넓은 스펙트럼 특징이 크게 겹칩니다. 따라서 개별 동위원소의 기여도를 분리하고 혼합물 내의 모든 성분을 정확하게 식별하는 것이 매우 어렵습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2020Evaluation">H. C. Lee et al. (2020)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>정확하고 신뢰성 있는 핵종 식별에 미치는 영향:
<ul>
<li>플라스틱 섬광체만으로는 에너지 스펙트럼을 알려진 감마선 에너지(광전 피크)와 직접 매칭하여 핵종을 정확하게 식별하는 것이 많은 핵종에서 거의 불가능합니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>보안 응용 분야에서 핵종을 정확하게 식별할 수 없으면 불법 물질과 유사한 에너지를 방출하는 자연 방사성 물질(NORM)로 인해 오경보율이 높아질 수 있습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2020Evaluation">H. C. Lee et al. (2020)</span>) 이러한 오경보는 운영 중단을 초래하고 2차 검사 관련 비용을 증가시킬 수 있습니다.</li>
<li>혼합 선원 내 개별 핵종의 활동도를 정확하게 정량화하는 것은 뚜렷한 스펙트럼 특징의 부족과 겹치는 콤프턴 연속 스펙트럼의 특성으로 인해 심각하게 저해됩니다.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-2">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Insight 5</strong>: 플라스틱 섬광체가 나타내는 에너지 분해능의 고유한 한계는 명확하고 모호하지 않은 핵종 식별을 요구하는 응용 분야에서 중요한 장벽으로 작용합니다. 따라서 제한된 스펙트럼 데이터에서 더 많은 식별 정보를 추출할 수 있는 특수 기술 개발이 필요합니다.
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: 감마선과 플라스틱 섬광체(주로 콤프턴 산란)의 상호작용을 지배하는 물리적 과정은 근본적이며 쉽게 변경할 수 없습니다. 따라서 이러한 검출기를 사용한 핵종 식별의 발전은 이러한 고유한 물리적 한계를 극복하기 위한 정교한 데이터 처리 및 분석 방법에 초점을 맞춰야 합니다.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Insight 6</strong>: 보안 감시에서 높은 오경보율과 혼합 선원 정량화의 어려움과 같은 낮은 에너지 분해능의 실제적인 결과는 개선된 식별 기술의 시급한 필요성을 강조합니다. 이러한 과제는 실제 응용 분야에서 플라스틱 섬광체의 분석 능력을 향상시킬 수 있는 고급 알고리즘 및 검출기 설계 연구의 중요성을 강조합니다.</li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="플라스틱-섬광체를-이용한-핵종-식별-기술-및-발전" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="플라스틱-섬광체를-이용한-핵종-식별-기술-및-발전"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> 플라스틱 섬광체를 이용한 핵종 식별 기술 및 발전:</h2>
<ul>
<li>에너지 분광학과 그 한계:
<ul>
<li>기본 원리: 감마선 분광학은 시료에서 방출되는 감마선의 에너지 분포를 측정하여 고유한 에너지 방출(고분해능 스펙트럼에서 광전 피크로 관찰됨)을 기반으로 구성 핵종을 식별하는 것을 포함합니다.<sup>23</sup></li>
<li>라스틱 섬광체의 한계: 콤프턴 산란이 주를 이루고 에너지 분해능이 낮기 때문에 플라스틱 섬광체로 얻은 에너지 스펙트럼에는 직접적이고 명확한 핵종 식별에 필요한 뚜렷한 광전 피크가 부족한 경향이 있습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>) 스펙트럼은 산란된 광자의 넓은 에너지 분포인 콤프턴 연속 스펙트럼이 주를 이룹니다.</li>
<li>콤프턴 에지 분석: 콤프턴 에지는 콤프턴 산란 사건에서 전자에 전달되는 최대 에너지를 나타내며, 스펙트럼에서 결정될 수 있으며 입사 감마선의 최대 에너지에 대한 일부 정보를 제공합니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Kim2018EnergyResolution">Kim et al. (2018)</span>) 그러나 콤프턴 에지 에너지는 특정 핵종에 고유하지 않으며 정확한 결정은 검출기의 에너지 분해능에 영향을 받아 명확한 식별에 대한 유용성이 제한됩니다.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>펄스 모양 구별법(Pulse Shape Discrimination, PSD):
<ul>
<li>PSD는 섬광체 물질 내 에너지 손실률(dE/dx)을 기반으로 다른 유형의 방사선(예: 감마선 및 중성자)에 의해 생성된 섬광 펄스의 시간적 모양의 미묘한 차이를 활용하는 기술입니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2024PulseShape">Y. Lee et al. (2024)</span>)중성자는 핵과의 상호작용으로 인해 감마선에 비해 느린 감쇠 성분을 갖는 펄스를 생성하는 경향이 있습니다. 감마선은 주로 전자와 상호작용합니다.</li>
<li>주요 응용 분야: PSD는 유기 섬광체(플라스틱 포함)에서 중성자와 감마선 유도 신호를 구별하는 데 매우 효과적이며 혼합 방사선장 측정에 널리 사용됩니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Pozzi2013PulseShape">Pozzi, Bourne, and Clarke (2013)</span>)</li>
<li>감마선 핵종 식별에 대한 직접적인 사용 제한(플라스틱 섬광체의 에너지 스펙트럼만 기반): PSD는 중성자와 감마선을 구별할 수 있지만, 감마 에너지 스펙트럼만으로는 다른 감마 방출 핵종을 구별하기에 충분한 정보를 일반적으로 제공하지 않습니다. 플라스틱 섬광체에서 서로 다른 감마 에너지 또는 서로 다른 감마 방출 핵종에서 생성된 시간적 펄스 모양은 매우 유사한 경향이 있어 PSD를 감마 에너지 범위 내에서 상세한 핵종 식별에 사용하는 것이 어렵습니다.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>에너지 가중 알고리즘(Energy-Weighted Algorithms):
<ul>
<li>원리: 에너지 가중 알고리즘은 각 채널의 에너지를 기반으로 가중치를 할당하여 원시 에너지 스펙트럼을 수정함으로써 플라스틱 섬광체에서 얻은 스펙트럼 정보를 향상시키는 것을 목표로 합니다. 이는 종종 각 채널의 계수율에 에너지 관련 계수를 곱하는 것을 포함하며, 특히 콤프턴 최대값을 강조하여 더 뚜렷하고 식별 가능한 피크로 나타나도록 만듭니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>학적 공식: 일반적인 접근 방식은 각 채널(i)의 에너지 가중 계수(EWAi​)를 원래 계수(Ci​)에 해당 채널의 에너지 계수(Ei​)를 곱하여 계산하는 것입니다(EWAi​=Ci​×Ei​).(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2016Validation">H. Lee et al. (2016)</span>) 정 응용 분야에 맞게 알고리즘을 최적화하기 위해 정수 상수를 도입하는 등 다양한 변형이 연구되었습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2020Evaluation">H. C. Lee et al. (2020)</span>)</li>
<li>개선 메커니즘: 입사 감마선의 최대 에너지와 관련된 콤프턴 에지 영역을 강조함으로써 에너지 가중 알고리즘은 플라스틱 섬광체의 낮은 에너지 분해능에서도 서로 다른 핵종에 대해 더 특징적인 스펙트럼 서명을 생성하는 데 도움이 될 수 있습니다.<sup>24</sup> 이러한 변환은 콤프턴 에지의 점진적인 분포를 더 뚜렷한 피크로 변환할 수 있습니다.</li>
<li>검증 연구: 수많은 연구에서 실험실 실험과 방사선 포털 모니터(RPM)와 같은 실제 응용 분야 모두에서 플라스틱 섬광체를 사용하여 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E%7B137%7D">Cs, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E%7B60%7D">Co, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E%7B22%7D">Na 및 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E%7B40%7D">K와 같은 다양한 핵종 간의 식별 능력을 향상시키는 데 에너지 가중 알고리즘의 효과가 입증되었습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>) 이러한 알고리즘은 인공 방사성 핵종과 자연 방사성 물질(NORM)을 구별하는 데에도 잠재력을 보여주었습니다.<sup>25</sup></li>
<li>제한 사항: 에너지 가중 알고리즘의 효과는 특히 콤프턴 에지 또는 에너지 가중 피크가 크게 겹치는 경우, 복잡한 핵종 혼합물을 처리할 때 감소할 수 있습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2020Evaluation">H. C. Lee et al. (2020)</span>) 또한 RPM 응용 분야에서 차폐 및 이동하는 선원의 속도와 같은 요인에 의해 성능이 영향을 받을 수 있습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>머신러닝 접근법:
<ul>
<li>원리: 컨볼루션 신경망(CNN), 인공 신경망(ANN), 서포트 벡터 머신(SVM), 트랜스포머 기반 네트워크와 같은 머신러닝 모델은 알려진 핵종의 플라스틱 섬광체 스펙트럼의 대규모 데이터셋으로 훈련되어 미지의 스펙트럼에서 패턴을 인식하고 분류하는 데 점점 더 많이 적용되고 있습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>데이터 전처리: 일반적인 기술로는 배경 잡음 제거, 스펙트럼을 일관된 스케일로 정규화, CNN 입력으로 활용하기 위해 1차원 스펙트럼 데이터를 2차원 이미지 표현으로 변환하는 것 등이 있습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Istofa2025RadionuclideIdentification">Istofa et al. (2025)</span>)</li>
<li>성능 평가: 연구에서는 플라스틱 섬광체 스펙트럼으로 훈련된 머신러닝 모델을 사용하여 개별 핵종 및 혼합 핵종을 식별하는 데 높은 예측 정확도(종종 90%를 초과하고 특정 조건에서는 최대 98%까지 도달)가 보고되었습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>) 이러한 모델은 유사한 콤프턴 에지 에너지를 가진 핵종을 식별하고 역동적인 선원 이동 및 차폐 존재와 같은 다양한 어려운 조건에서도 강력한 식별 성능을 보여주었습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>과제 해결: 머신러닝 접근법은 낮은 에너지 분해능과 광전 피크 부재와 같은 한계를 극복할 수 있는 잠재력을 보여주었습니다. CNN은 특히 컨볼루션 및 풀링 연산을 통해 스펙트럼 데이터에서 관련 특징을 추출하는 데 유망합니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Turner2021ConvolutionalNeuralNetwork">Turner et al. (2021)</span>)</li>
<li>설명 가능한 AI(XAI): 특히 딥러닝 네트워크와 같은 머신러닝 모델은 종종 “블랙박스”로 간주되므로, 핵종 식별과 같은 중요한 응용 분야에서 의사 결정 과정을 이해하고 해석하기 위해 XAI 기술을 사용하는 것에 대한 관심이 증가하고 있습니다. Saliency mapping 및 Grad-CAM(Gradient-weighted Class Activation Mapping)과 같은 방법이 모델이 분류를 수행할 때 에너지 스펙트럼의 어느 부분에 초점을 맞추는지 식별하는 데 연구되고 있습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Jeon2023Explanation">Jeon, Kim, and and (2023)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>다중 배열 플라스틱 섬광체 검출기:
<ul>
<li>원리: 단일 대용량 검출기 대신 여러 개의 작은 플라스틱 섬광체를 배열로 사용하여 전체 광자 수집 효율을 개선하고 잠재적으로 방사선원에 대한 공간 정보를 제공하여 식별에 도움이 될 수 있습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>입증된 장점: 다중 배열 검출기는 기존의 단일 소자 검출기에 비해 섬광체 내에서 생성된 광자를 수집할 확률이 더 높은 것으로 나타났습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>알고리즘과의 결합: 에너지 가중 알고리즘 및 머신러닝 모델과 결합했을 때, 다중 배열 시스템은 움직이는 방사선원을 식별하는 데 향상된 성능을 보여주었습니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>하이브리드 검출 시스템:
<ul>
<li>원리: 플라스틱 섬광체를 높은 에너지 분해능과 같은 상호 보완적인 강점을 제공하는 검출기(예: 고순도 게르마늄 - HPGe 검출기)와 결합하면 핵종 식별 능력을 향상시킬 수 있습니다. 플라스틱 섬광체는 큰 부피로 인해 높은 검출 효율을 제공할 수 있는 반면, HPGe 검출기는 동시 계수 기술을 통해 또는 높은 에너지 분해능으로 이벤트의 하위 집합을 분석하여 명확한 식별을 위한 정확한 에너지 측정을 제공할 수 있습니다(<span class="citation" data-cites="Goodwin2023PlasticScintillator">Goodwin et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>고급 섬광체 재료 및 첨가제:
<ul>
<li>지속적인 연구는 광 수율을 향상시키고 잠재적으로 에너지 분해능을 높이며 분광학적 응용을 위한 더 나은 펄스 모양 구별을 가능하게 하기 위해 새로운 플라스틱 섬광체 재료를 개발하고 특정 화합물(예: 유기 주석)을 고분자 매트릭스에 통합하는 데 초점을 맞추고 있습니다.<sup>26</sup> 여기에는 열악한 환경에서의 사용을 위한 방사선 경화 플라스틱에 대한 연구도 포함됩니다.</li>
<li>폴리스타이렌과 폴리메틸메타크릴레이트(PMMA)와 같은 서로 다른 고분자를 혼합한 하이브리드 플라스틱 섬광체의 개발은 광학적 투명성과 기계적 내구성을 향상시키는 데 유망하며, 이는 더 효율적이고 신뢰할 수 있는 검출기로 이어질 수 있습니다.<sup>27</sup></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-3">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Insight 7</strong>: 플라스틱 섬광체를 이용한 핵종 식별 기술은 재료 과학, 검출기 설계 및 전산 지능의 발전을 결합하는 시너지 효과를 통해 발전할 가능성이 높습니다. 이는 단일 혁신적인 돌파구보다는 여러 연구 분야에서 발생하는 점진적인 개선을 통해 진전이 이루어질 것임을 시사합니다.
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: 플라스틱 섬광체의 고유한 물리적 한계는 재료 개선만으로는 완전히 극복하기 어려울 것입니다. 더 나은 재료를 보다 정교한 알고리즘 및 검출기 구성과 통합하는 것이 플라스틱 섬광체의 핵종 식별 능력을 크게 향상시키는 가장 유망한 방법입니다.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Insight 8</strong>: 머신러닝 및 AI 기반 분석의 증가는 휴대용 및 현장 배치 가능한 플라스틱 섬광체 시스템이 이전에는 더 정교하고 덜 이동성이 좋은 검출기 기술로만 달성할 수 있었던 수준의 핵종 식별 정확도를 달성할 수 있는 잠재력을 시사합니다. 이는 특히 보안 및 비상 대응 시나리오에서 다양한 분야에 상당한 영향을 미칠 수 있습니다.
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: 사고의 흐름: 머신러닝 모델이 대규모 스펙트럼 정보 데이터셋에서 복잡한 패턴을 학습할 수 있는 능력은 기존 분석 방법으로는 쉽게 드러나지 않는 식별 특징을 추출할 수 있는 유망한 경로를 제공합니다. 이는 휴대성과 비용 효율성을 유지하면서도 매우 효과적인 핵종 식별 시스템 개발로 이어질 수 있습니다.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="다른-핵종-식별-기술과의-비교" class="level2" data-number="5">
<h2 data-number="5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="다른-핵종-식별-기술과의-비교"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> 다른 핵종 식별 기술과의 비교:</h2>
<div id="tbl-comparison_of_RIT" class="striped hover quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-comparison_of_RIT-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
표&nbsp;1: Comparison of Radionuclide Identification Technologies for Gamma-Ray Spectroscopy
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-comparison_of_RIT-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="table-striped table-hover caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 21%">
<col style="width: 26%">
<col style="width: 26%">
<col style="width: 26%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: center;">Feature</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Plastic Scintillator</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Inorganic Scintillator (NaI(Tl))</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Semiconductor Detector (HPGe)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Energy Resolution</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low (10-15% at 662 keV)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Medium (6-8% at 662 keV)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Excellent (&lt;1% at 662 keV)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Density</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Effective Atomic Number</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Cost</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Medium</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Portability</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High (lightweight, rugged)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Medium</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low (requires cooling)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Photopeak Presence</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Weak or absent due to Compton dominance</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Distinct</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Distinct</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Gamma-Ray Sensitivity</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Medium</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Neutron Sensitivity</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low (can be doped for thermal neutrons)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Low (can be doped for thermal neutrons)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Sensitive to fast neutrons</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Response Speed</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Fast (nanoseconds)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Medium (microseconds)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Slow (microseconds)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Main Applications</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">RPM, high count rate environments, beta detection, wide area monitoring</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Medical imaging, general gamma-ray spectroscopy, field RIID</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">High-resolution spectroscopy, low-level counting</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Radionuclide ID Ability</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Limited (requires advanced algorithms or hybrid systems)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Good (based on photopeaks)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Excellent (precise energy measurement)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>무기 섬광체(NaI(Tl), CsI(Tl), LaBr3):</strong> 플라스틱 섬광체보다 에너지 분해능이 훨씬 우수하여 특징적인 광전 피크 분석을 통해 보다 직접적이고 신뢰성 있는 핵종 식별이 가능합니다.<sup>28</sup><sup>,</sup> <sup>29</sup> 예를 들어, NaI(Tl)은 높은 광 수율과 좋은 분해능을 가지고 있어 핵종 식별 장비에 적합합니다.<sup>30</sup> LaBr3 섬광체는 NaI(Tl)보다 더 나은 분해능을 제공합니다.<sup>31</sup>그러나 무기 섬광체는 일반적으로 더 비싸고 일부는 흡습성이 있어 취급 및 포장에 주의가 필요합니다.<sup>32</sup><sup>,</sup><sup>33</sup></p></li>
<li><p><strong>반도체 검출기(HPGe, CZT):</strong> 일반적으로 사용되는 방사선 검출기 중에서 최고의 에너지 분해능을 제공하여 복잡한 핵종 혼합물을 매우 정확하게 식별하고 낮은 활동도 선원을 검출할 수 있습니다.<sup>34</sup><sup>,</sup><sup>35</sup> HPGe 검출기는 작동을 위해 극저온 냉각이 필요하여 휴대성이 제한되고 작동 복잡성이 증가합니다. CZT 검출기는 실온에서 작동할 수 있지만 섬광체보다 일반적으로 더 비쌉니다.<sup>36</sup><sup>,</sup> <sup>37</sup></p></li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-4">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Insight 9:</strong> 핵종 식별을 위한 검출기 기술의 선택은 에너지 분해능 및 검출 효율과 같은 성능 특성과 비용, 휴대성 및 작동 복잡성과 같은 실제 고려 사항 간의 절충을 포함합니다. 플라스틱 섬광체는 분광학적 정확도를 다소 희생하더라도 비용, 크기 및 속도가 가장 중요한 시나리오에서 장점을 제공합니다.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought:</strong> 항만에서의 고속 처리량 검색(RPM)은 비용이 많이 드는 고분해능 검출기보다 플라스틱 섬광체를 선호하는 반면, 환경 모니터링을 위한 실험실 환경에서는 미량의 핵종을 정확하게 식별하기 위해 HPGe 검출기의 높은 분해능을 우선시할 수 있습니다.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Insight 10:</strong> 플라스틱 섬광체를 다른 검출기 유형과 결합한 하이브리드 시스템의 개발은 서로 다른 기술의 상호 보완적인 강점을 활용하려는 노력을 나타냅니다. 이 접근 방식은 단일 검출기가 모든 시나리오에 이상적이지 않다는 점을 인식하고 핵종 식별을 위한 보다 다재다능하고 고성능 솔루션을 만드는 것을 목표로 합니다.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="휴대용-및-현장-배치-가능-시스템의-예" class="level2" data-number="6">
<h2 data-number="6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="휴대용-및-현장-배치-가능-시스템의-예"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> 휴대용 및 현장 배치 가능 시스템의 예:</h2>
<ul>
<li>방사선 포털 모니터(RPM): 1차 검색을 위해 대용량 플라스틱 섬광체를 일반적으로 사용합니다.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>) 향상된 식별 능력을 위해 에너지 가중 알고리즘 및 머신러닝과 결합되는 경우가 많습니다(여전히 제한적임).(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>)</li>
<li>휴대용 핵종 식별 장치(RIID): 최초 대응자, 법 집행 기관 및 보안 담당자를 위해 설계된 많은 휴대용 RIID는 민감도, 빠른 응답 및 현장 사용을 위한 견고성의 균형을 달성하기 위해 플라스틱 섬광체를 통합합니다.<sup>38</sup> 이러한 장치에는 획득한 스펙트럼을 기반으로 어느 정도의 핵종 식별 기능을 제공하는 알고리즘이 포함되어 있는 경우가 많습니다.</li>
<li>착용형 개인 방사선 선량계: 소형 플라스틱 섬광체와 SiPM을 결합하여 개인 방사선 노출을 실시간으로 모니터링하기 위해 개발되고 있습니다.<sup>39</sup> 주로 선량 측정을 위한 것이지만 일부 고급 모델은 기본적인 핵종 식별 기능을 제공할 수 있습니다.</li>
<li>배낭형 방사선 검출 시스템: 넓은 지역에서 방사선원을 검색하기 위해 설계된 휴대용 시스템에는 감마선 및 중성자 검출을 위해 플라스틱 섬광체가 포함될 수 있습니다.<sup>40</sup> 이러한 시스템에는 데이터 분석 및 잠재적인 동위원소 식별을 위한 소프트웨어가 포함되어 있는 경우가 많습니다.</li>
<li>플라스틱 섬광 광섬유(PSOF) 검출기: 유연하고 길이가 긴 이 검출기는 오염된 지역 및 액체 환경에서 방사선 감시를 위해 현장에 배치할 수 있으며 유연성과 확장된 범위를 제공합니다.[^27] 적절한 분석 기술과 결합하면 특정 핵종의 존재에 대한 정보를 제공할 수 있습니다.</li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-5" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-5">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications:</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Insight 11</strong>: 플라스틱 섬광체를 기반으로 하는 다양한 휴대용 시스템의 개발은 특히 보안 및 비상 대응 시나리오에서 핵종 검출 및 식별을 위한 현장 배치 가능한 솔루션에 대한 지속적인 필요성을 입증합니다. 이러한 시나리오에서는 플라스틱 섬광체의 장점(크기, 무게, 비용)이 분광학적 한계보다 중요합니다.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: 핵 및 방사능 테러의 위협 증가와 사고 발생 시 신속한 환경 감시의 필요성은 휴대하기 쉽고 사용자 친화적인 검출 시스템에 대한 수요를 촉진합니다. 플라스틱 섬광체는 이러한 시스템에 쉽게 통합될 수 있어 이러한 요구 사항을 해결하는 데 중요한 역할을 합니다.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="최근-발전-및-미래-추세" class="level2" data-number="7">
<h2 data-number="7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="최근-발전-및-미래-추세"><span class="header-section-number">7</span> 최근 발전 및 미래 추세:</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>플라스틱 섬광체의 식별 능력을 향상시키기 위해 에너지 가중 알고리즘 및 머신러닝 모델(딥러닝 아키텍처 포함)의 지속적인 개발 및 개선.(<span class="citation" data-cites="Lee2023Radionuclide">H. C. Lee et al. (2023)</span>) 정확도 향상, 복잡한 혼합물 처리, 오경보율 감소에 초점.</p></li>
<li><p>향상된 광 수율과 잠재적으로 더 나은 에너지 분해능을 위해 새로운 유기 화합물 또는 중금속 첨가제를 포함하는 새로운 플라스틱 섬광체 재료에 대한 연구<sup>41</sup> 열악한 환경에서의 사용을 위한 방사선 경화 플라스틱 개발도 포함됩니다.</p></li>
<li><p>특히 SiPM과 같은 광센서 기술의 발전으로 휴대용 시스템을 더욱 작고 견고하며 전력 효율적으로 만들 수 있는 잠재력 제공.<sup>42</sup></p></li>
<li><p>높은 효율성과 좋은 에너지 분해능의 균형을 달성하기 위해 플라스틱 섬광체를 다른 유형의 검출기와 결합한 하이브리드 검출기 설계 연구.</p></li>
<li><p>섬광 펄스에서 추가 정보를 추출하고 잠재적으로 다른 핵종의 식별을 개선하기 위한 보다 정교한 신호 처리 기술 개발.</p></li>
<li><p>중요한 응용 분야에서 핵종 식별에 사용되는 머신러닝 모델의 설명 가능성 및 해석 가능성에 대한 관심 증가(<span class="citation" data-cites="Jeon2023Explanation">Jeon, Kim, and and (2023)</span>)</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-6" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-hidden-patterns-causal-relationships-and-broad-implications-6">Insights, Hidden Patterns, Causal Relationships, and Broad Implications:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Insight 12</strong>: 플라스틱 섬광체를 이용한 핵종 식별의 미래는 재료 과학, 검출기 공학 및 전산 지능의 융합적인 발전에 크게 의존할 것입니다. 이는 획기적인 단일 기술보다는 여러 연구 분야에서 발생하는 점진적인 개선을 통해 발전이 이루어질 가능성이 높다는 것을 시사합니다.
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought:</strong> 플라스틱 섬광체의 고유한 물리적 한계를 재료 개선만으로는 완전히 극복하기 어려울 것입니다. 더 나은 재료를 보다 정교한 알고리즘 및 검출기 구성과 통합하는 것이 플라스틱 섬광체의 핵종 식별 능력을 크게 향상시키는 가장 유망한 방법입니다.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Insight 13</strong>: 머신러닝 및 AI 기반 분석의 증가는 휴대용 및 현장 배치 가능한 플라스틱 섬광체 시스템이 이전에는 더 정교하고 덜 이동성이 좋은 검출기 기술로만 달성할 수 있었던 수준의 핵종 식별 정확도를 달성할 수 있는 잠재력을 시사합니다. 이는 특히 보안 및 비상 대응 시나리오에서 다양한 분야에 상당한 영향을 미칠 수 있습니다.
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain of Thought</strong>: 머신러닝 모델이 대규모 스펙트럼 정보 데이터셋에서 복잡한 패턴을 학습할 수 있는 능력은 기존 분석 방법으로는 쉽게 드러나지 않는 식별 특징을 추출할 수 있는 유망한 경로를 제공합니다. 이는 휴대성과 비용 효율성을 유지하면서도 매우 효과적인 핵종 식별 시스템 개발로 이어질 수 있습니다.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="결론" class="level2" data-number="8">
<h2 data-number="8" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="결론"><span class="header-section-number">8</span> 결론:</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>플라스틱 섬광체를 이용한 핵종 식별의 현재 능력 및 한계 요약: 비용 효율성, 빠른 속도 및 휴대성 면에서 장점을 제공하지만, 낮은 에너지 분해능은 정확한 핵종 식별에 상당한 어려움을 야기합니다.</p></li>
<li><p>발전 사항 요약: 에너지 가중 알고리즘 및 머신러닝 기술의 적용을 통해 제한된 스펙트럼 데이터에서 더 많은 식별 정보를 추출함으로써 상당한 진전이 이루어졌습니다. 다중 배열 및 하이브리드 검출기 설계 또한 향상된 성능을 위한 잠재력을 보여줍니다.</p></li>
<li><p>Future outlook: 고급 재료, 혁신적인 검출기 설계 및 정교한 전산 방법을 지속적으로 연구함으로써 이 분야가 더욱 발전할 가능성이 높습니다. 플라스틱 섬광체가 모든 응용 분야에서 고분해능 검출기를 완전히 대체하지는 못하겠지만, 지속적인 혁신을 통해 특히 휴대용 및 현장 배치 가능한 시스템과 같이 고유한 장점이 중요한 시나리오에서 핵종 식별 분야에서 그 역할이 확대될 것으로 예상됩니다.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
<section id="references" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h3>
<div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-Ely2008TheUse" class="csl-entry">
Ely, James, Kevin Anderson, Derrick Bates, Richard Kouzes, C. Presti, Robert Runkle, Edward Siciliano, and Dennis Weier. 2008. <span>‘The Use of Energy Information in Plastic Scintillator Material’</span>. <em>Journal of Radioanalytical and Nuclear Chemistry - J RADIOANAL NUCL CHEM</em> 276 (June): 743–48. https://doi.org/<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10967-008-0627-5">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10967-008-0627-5</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Goodwin2023PlasticScintillator" class="csl-entry">
Goodwin, M A, T P Gill, A V Davies, R Britton, S J Bell, and P H Regan. 2023. <span>‘A Plastic Scintillator and HPGe β-Γcoincidence Detection System.’</span> <em>Appl Radiat Isot</em> 201 (November): 111028. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apradiso.2023.111028">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apradiso.2023.111028</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hafzoglu2024Efficiency" class="csl-entry">
Hafızoğlu, Nurgül. 2024. <span>‘Efficiency and Energy Resolution of Gamma Spectrometry System with HPGe Detector Depending on Variable Source-to-Detector Distances’</span>. <em>The European Physical Journal Plus</em> 139 (2): 134. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1140/epjp/s13360-024-04903-y">https://doi.org/10.1140/epjp/s13360-024-04903-y</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Istofa2025RadionuclideIdentification" class="csl-entry">
Istofa, Istofa, Gina Kusuma, Firliyani Ningsih, Joko Triyanto, I Putu Susila, and Prawito Prajitno. 2025. <span>‘Radionuclide Identification System Using Convolution Neural Network for Environmental Radiation Monitoring’</span>. <em>International Journal of Electrical and Computer Engineering (IJECE)</em> 15 (April): 2282. <a href="https://doi.org/10.11591/ijece.v15i2.pp2282-2290">https://doi.org/10.11591/ijece.v15i2.pp2282-2290</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jeon2023Explanation" class="csl-entry">
Jeon, Byoungil, Jinhwan Kim, and Myungkook Moon and. 2023. <span>‘Explanation of Deep Learning–Based Radioisotope Identifier for Plastic Scintillation Detector’</span>. <em>Nuclear Technology</em> 209 (1): 1–14. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/00295450.2022.2096389">https://doi.org/10.1080/00295450.2022.2096389</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Kim2018EnergyResolution" class="csl-entry">
Kim, Yonghyun, Jaebum Son, Junesic Park, Dong-geon Kim, Kihong Pak Pak, Sangmin Lee, and Yong Kyun Kim. 2018. <span>‘Energy Resolution of the Fabricated Plastic Scintillator’</span>. Korean Nuclear Society; Korean Nuclear Society.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lee2020Evaluation" class="csl-entry">
Lee, Hyun Cheol, Bon Tack Koo, Chang Il Choi, Chang Su Park, Jeongwan Kwon, Hong-Suk Kim, Heejun Chung, and Min Chul Hee. 2020. <span>‘Evaluation of Source Identification Method Based on Energy-Weighting Level with Portal Monitoring System Using Plastic Scintillator’</span>. <em>J. Radiat. Prot. Res</em> 45 (3): 117–29. <a href="https://doi.org/10.14407/jrpr.2020.45.3.117">https://doi.org/10.14407/jrpr.2020.45.3.117</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lee2023Radionuclide" class="csl-entry">
Lee, Hyun Cheol, Bon Tack Koo, Ju Young Jeon, Bo-Wi Cheon, Do Hyeon Yoo, Heejun Chung, and Chul Hee Min. 2023. <span>‘Radionuclide Identification Based on Energy-Weighted Algorithm and Machine Learning Applied to a Multi-Array Plastic Scintillator’</span>. <em>Nuclear Engineering and Technology</em> 55 (10): 3907–12. https://doi.org/<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.net.2023.07.005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.net.2023.07.005</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lee2016Validation" class="csl-entry">
Lee, Hyun, Wook-Geun Shin, Hyo Park, Dohyeon Yoo, Chang-Il Choi, Chang-Su Park, Hong-Suk Kim, and Chul Hee Min. 2016. <span>‘Validation of Energy-Weighted Algorithm for Radiation Portal Monitor Using Plastic Scintillator’</span>. <em>Applied Radiation and Isotopes</em> 107 (January): 160–64. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apradiso.2015.10.019">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apradiso.2015.10.019</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lee2024PulseShape" class="csl-entry">
Lee, Yujin, Jinyoung Kim, Byoung-cheol Koh, Young Soo Yoon, and Chang Hyon Ha. 2024. <span>‘Pulse Shape Discrimination in an Organic Scintillation Phoswich Detector Using Machine Learning Techniques’</span>. <em>Frontiers in Physics</em> Volume 12 - 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphy.2024.1361608">https://doi.org/10.3389/fphy.2024.1361608</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mengesha2015PlascitScintillators" class="csl-entry">
Mengesha, Wondwosen, Patrick L Feng, Joseph Gabriel Cordaro, Mitchell Anstey, Nicholas Myllenbeck, and Daniel J. Throckmorton. 2015. <span>‘Plastic Scintillators Light Yield Energy Calibration.’</span>, December. <a href="https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1427195">https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1427195</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Persyk1978StateOfTheArt" class="csl-entry">
Persyk, D. E., and T. E. Moi. 1978. <span>‘State-of-the-Art Photomultipliers for Anger Cameras’</span>. <em>IEEE Transactions on Nuclear Science</em> 25 (1): 615–19. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/TNS.1978.4329382">https://doi.org/10.1109/TNS.1978.4329382</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Pozzi2013PulseShape" class="csl-entry">
Pozzi, Sara, Mark Bourne, and Shaun Clarke. 2013. <span>‘Pulse Shape Discrimination in the Plastic Scintillator EJ-299-33’</span>. <em>Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section A: Accelerators, Spectrometers, Detectors and Associated Equipment</em> 723 (September): 19–23. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nima.2013.04.085">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nima.2013.04.085</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Turner2021ConvolutionalNeuralNetwork" class="csl-entry">
Turner, Anthony, Carl Wheldon, Tzany Kokalova Wheldon, Mark Gilbert, Lee Packer, Jonathan Burns, and Martin Freer. 2021. <span>‘Convolutional Neural Networks for Challenges in Automated Nuclide Identification’</span>. <em>Sensors</em> 21 (August): 5238. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/s21155238">https://doi.org/10.3390/s21155238</a>.
</div>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="참고자료" class="level2" data-number="9">
<h2 data-number="9" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="참고자료"><span class="header-section-number">9</span> 참고자료</h2>
<p>[2] Feasibility study for radionuclide identification using multi-array …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/338055509_Feasibility_study_for_radionuclide_identification_using_multi-array_plastic_scintillator_and_energy_weighted_algorithm_of_radiation_portal_monitors_a_Monte_Carlo_study</p>
<p>[3] Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/</p>
<p>[4] Scintillator - Wikipedia, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scintillator</p>
<p>[5] SB 40/150 Plastic Scintillators - Mirion Technologies, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.mirion.com/products/technologies/radiation-monitoring-systems/pro-tk-radiation-and-process-monitoring-systems/radiation-detectors-1e/sb-40-150-plastic-scintillators</p>
<p>[6] Plastic Scintillators | Oncology Medical Physics, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://oncologymedicalphysics.com/plastic-scintillators/</p>
<p>[7] Scintillation Detectors ⋆ Scionix, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://scionix.nl/scintillation-detectors/</p>
<p>[8] Scintillators - OSTI, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1867988</p>
<p>[9] Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors</p>
<p>[10] Scintillators!, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.oeaw.ac.at/fileadmin/Institute/HEPHY/PDF/ausbildung/praktikum/VO-5-Scintillators.pdf</p>
<p>[11] Energy resolution of plastic scintillation detector for beta rays, H. H. Vo et. al.&nbsp;<em>IEEE Transactions on Nuclear Science</em>, <strong>55</strong> (6):3717-3724, 2008 DOI: 10.1109/TNS.2008.2005718, https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/4723822</p>
<p>[12] Unlocking the Secrets of Radiation: Marvel of the Scintillation Counter - Open MedScience, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://openmedscience.com/unlocking-the-secrets-of-radiation-marvel-of-the-scintillation-counter/</p>
<p>[16] Silicon Photomultiplier (SiPM) Readout of Scintillators | Berkeley …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/silicon-photomultiplier-readout</p>
<p>[17] Scintillation detector with SiPM matrix as a photosensor | Request PDF, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/322680188_Scintillation_detector_with_SiPM_matrix_as_a_photosensor</p>
<p>[20] PULSE SHAPE DISCRIMINATION IN A PLASTIC SCINTILLATOR (Journal Article) - OSTI, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.osti.gov/biblio/4140599</p>
<p>[21] EJ-276D - Pulse Shape Discrimination Plastic Scintillator - Eljen Technology, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://eljentechnology.com/products/plastic-scintillators/ej-276</p>
<p>[22] Pulse shape simulations for organic scintillation detectors using Geant4 - EPJ Web of Conferences, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.epj-conferences.org/articles/epjconf/pdf/2021/07/epjconf_animma2021_11002.pdf</p>
<p>[23] Validation of energy-weighted algorithm for radiation portal monitor using plastic scintillator, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/283844276_Validation_of_energy-weighted_algorithm_for_radiation_portal_monitor_using_plastic_scintillator</p>
<p>[25] A Monte Carlo study of an energy-weighted algorithm for radionuclide analysis with a plastic scintillation detector - ResearchGate, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/274397333_A_Monte_Carlo_study_of_an_energy-weighted_algorithm_for_radionuclide_analysis_with_a_plastic_scintillation_detector</p>
<p>[28] Development of a radionuclide identification algorithm based on a convolutional neural network for radiation portal monitoring system - INIS-IAEA, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://inis.iaea.org/records/cdxny-y9z44</p>
<p>[29] Comparison of Machine Learning-Based Radioisotope Identifiers for Plastic Scintillation Detector - Korea Science, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://koreascience.kr/article/JAKO202108458484352.page</p>
<p>[30] Comparison of Machine Learning-Based Radioisotope Identifiers for Plastic Scintillation Detector - Journal of Radiation Protection and Research, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.jrpr.org/include/download.php?filedata=1098%7Cjrpr-2021-00206.pdf</p>
<p>[34] Explaining machine-learning models for gamma-ray detection and identification - PMC, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10281578/</p>
<p>[35] Explaining machine-learning models for gamma-ray detection and identification | PLOS One, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0286829</p>
<p>[36] Pseudo-Gamma Spectroscopy Based on Plastic Scintillation Detectors Using Multitask Learning - MDPI, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/21/3/684</p>
<p>[40] Data Support of Generalization Ability of a CNN γ-ray Localization Model for Radiation Imaging, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.scidb.cn/en/detail?dataSetId=4ba07b2a777743d8938e920c3c258815</p>
<p>[43] Plastic Scintillators Light Yield Energy Calibration - OSTI, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1427195</p>
<p>[44] Hybrid plastic scintillators aim to improve nuclear safety and medical imaging - EurekAlert!, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/1068785</p>
<p>[45] Recent developments in plastic scintillators with pulse shape discrimination - ResearchGate, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/322877963_Recent_developments_in_plastic_scintillators_with_pulse_shape_discrimination</p>
<p>[46] Current status on plastic scintillators modifications (Conference) | OSTI.GOV, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.osti.gov/biblio/22531431</p>
<p>[47] Synthesis and Analysis of Novel Materials for Plastic Scintillators - eScholarship, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://escholarship.org/content/qt195786t5/qt195786t5.pdf?t=orl5aa</p>
<p>[48] Scintillation Radiation Detectors | Berkeley Nucleonics®, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/scintillation-crystals-detectors</p>
<p>[49] SAM 940 (RIID) Handheld Radiation Isotope Identifier - Berkeley Nucleonics, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/sam-940-riid</p>
<p>[50] RADEAGLET-R Rugged, Lightweight, Handheld Radioisotope Identification Device, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.ortec-online.com/products/portable-radioisotope-identification-devices-riids/radeaglet-r</p>
<p>[51] js-techwin.com, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://js-techwin.com/data/file/brochure/Products-JSTECHWIN%20(eng).pdf</p>
<p>[52] Portable Radiation Instruments - Handheld | LAURUS Systems, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.laurussystems.com/product-listing/handheld-radiation-instruments/</p>
<p>[53] Acquiring Gamma-Ray Energy Spectrum Using a Plastic Scintillation Optical Fiber Detector, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.mdpi.com/2304-6732/11/6/493</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">각주</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Scintillator - Wikipedia, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scintillator↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Scintillation Detectors ⋆ Scionix, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://scionix.nl/scintillation-detectors/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Scintillation Detectors ⋆ Scionix, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://scionix.nl/scintillation-detectors/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>Scintillator - Wikipedia, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scintillator↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>Scintillator - Wikipedia, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scintillator↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn8"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn9"><p>Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn10"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn11"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn12"><p>Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn13"><p>Scintillator - Wikipedia, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scintillator↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn14"><p>Scintillator - Wikipedia, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scintillator↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn15"><p>Scintillators!, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.oeaw.ac.at/fileadmin/Institute/HEPHY/PDF/ausbildung/praktikum/VO-5-Scintillators.pdf↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn16"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn17"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn18"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn19"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn20"><p>Silicon Photomultiplier (SiPM) Readout of Scintillators | Berkeley …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/silicon-photomultiplier-readout↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn21"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn22"><p>Silicon Photomultiplier (SiPM) Readout of Scintillators | Berkeley …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/silicon-photomultiplier-readout↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn23"><p>Scintillation Counters: What It Is and What It’s Used For - Moravek, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.moravek.com/scintillation-counters-what-it-is-and-what-its-used-for/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn24"><p>Feasibility study for radionuclide identification using multi-array …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/338055509_Feasibility_study_for_radionuclide_identification_using_multi-array_plastic_scintillator_and_energy_weighted_algorithm_of_radiation_portal_monitors_a_Monte_Carlo_study↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn25"><p>Feasibility study for radionuclide identification using multi-array …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.researchgate.net/publication/338055509_Feasibility_study_for_radionuclide_identification_using_multi-array_plastic_scintillator_and_energy_weighted_algorithm_of_radiation_portal_monitors_a_Monte_Carlo_study↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn26"><p>Scintillators - OSTI, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1867988↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn27"><p>Optical transmittance and pulse shape discrimination of polystyrene/poly(methyl methacrylate)-based plastic scintillators - EurekAlert!, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/1068785↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn28"><p>Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn29"><p>Scintillation Radiation Detectors | Berkeley Nucleonics®, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/scintillation-crystals-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn30"><p>Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn31"><p>Scintillation Radiation Detectors | Berkeley Nucleonics®, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/scintillation-crystals-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn32"><p>Scintillators!, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.oeaw.ac.at/fileadmin/Institute/HEPHY/PDF/ausbildung/praktikum/VO-5-Scintillators.pdf↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn33"><p>Scintillation Radiation Detectors | Berkeley Nucleonics®, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/scintillation-crystals-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn34"><p>Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn35"><p>Scintillation Radiation Detectors | Berkeley Nucleonics®, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/scintillation-crystals-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn36"><p>Plastic Scintillators VS Other Radiation Detectors - Shalom EO, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.shalomeo.com/plastic-scintillators-vs-other-radiation-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn37"><p>Scintillation Radiation Detectors | Berkeley Nucleonics®, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/scintillation-crystals-detectors↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn38"><p>SAM 940 (RIID) Handheld Radiation Isotope Identifier - Berkeley Nucleonics, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/sam-940-riid↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn39"><p>js-techwin.com, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://js-techwin.com/data/file/brochure/Products-JSTECHWIN%20(eng).pdf↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn40"><p>Portable Radiation Instruments - Handheld | LAURUS Systems, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.laurussystems.com/product-listing/handheld-radiation-instruments/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn41"><p>Scintillators - OSTI, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1867988↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn42"><p>Silicon Photomultiplier (SiPM) Readout of Scintillators | Berkeley …, 5월 18, 2025에 액세스, https://www.berkeleynucleonics.com/silicon-photomultiplier-readout↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://julia-kaeri.github.io/src/posts/plastic_scintillator_kor.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 12:31:30 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
